Leo Hurwitz collection, 1910-1992, bulk 1925-1991
George Eastman Museum
- Series 3, Film/TV Projects, 1930-1991; 1936-1987
  - Subseries 2,The Art of Seeing, 1966-1985; 1966/1969
    - no title (Box C068)
      - Selected for use in Bard, Spring '85, ca. 1968 (Folder 3g)
        Ideas for shooting the Cézanne painting and narration [possibly used later for a 1985 lecture at Bard College].
      - Journey Into/Discovery in a Painting-- cutting notes, 1968 (Folder 3h)
        Notes on the cutting and assembly of the prints.
      - Shooting materials -- "Color #4 Cézanne" -- shooting script notes and catalog, 1968 (Folder 3i)
        Shooting notes, notes on slides, and sketched layouts
      - [File Pocket containing film strips and slides], ca. 1968 (Folder 3j)
        Strips of 16mm color film, related to the Cézanne painting.
      - "Color #2" -- music and sound, outline of structure: notes, 1966; 1968 (Folder 5a)
        Notes and correspondence regarding the music, and shot list.
      - Wall schedule -- AFA films, ca. 1968 (Folder 5b)
        Shooting schedules for the American Federation of Arts (AFA) films 1, 2, and 3.
      - "Color #2" -- cutting notes and script ideas, 1968 (Folder 5c)
        Outline of the material with notes on the assembly of sections and overall thematic elements.
      - SFX and music logs -- "Color #2 Autumn", ca. 1968 (Folder 5d)
        Sound and music notes and log.
      - Music notes for recording, ca. 1968 (Folder 5e)
        Notes on the music in the form of a log with cues marked.
      - Organization of material -- "Color #2", ca. 1968 (Folder 5f)
        Sequence list/assembly sections, code numbers for the eight reels, and reel contents.
      - Words for "Color Film #2" -- draft narration -- L.H, 1966; 1968 (Folder 5g)
        "Autumn is a Painter" by Anthony J. Stanley; draft of the narration.
      - [Envelope labeled: Short clips and frames -- "Color #2"], ca. 1968 (Folder 5h)
        Strips of 16mm film.
      - Mix: log-loops, title, narration, shot list, 1968 (Folder 5i)
        Mix log; shot list; narration; and titles.
      - [Motion picture -- television permit; filming cooperation letter], 1967 (Folder 5j)
        New York City filming permit; letter from the American Federation of Arts (AFA) requesting blanket cooperation with Hurwitz.
      - [Envelopes labeled: "Color #2" or "#4" film clips], ca. 1968 (Folder 5k)
        Strips of 16mm film, inside an envelope and a folded piece of paper. Reel numbers listed.
      - [AFA outlines -- space and distortion], 1966 (Folder 9b)
        Outlines on the subjects of space and distortion, prepared by Roemer-Young Associates for the American Federation of Arts (AFA).
      - [Authorization form; introductory letter], 1967 (Folder 9c)
        Form authorizing children to appear in the film on color, with a letter stating that Hurwitz is working on behalf of the American Federation of Arts (AFA).
      - AFA budgets -- City 1A, Country 1B, ca. 1968 (Folder 9e)
        Budgets for Light and the Country and Light and the City.
      - AFA -- "Color" and other -- Script in outline beyond "notes" stage, 1967 (Folder 9f)
        Treatment script for "the first of two films on color" and outline.
    - no title (Box C086)
      - Lab costs: interneg, master, undated (Folder 13)
    - no title (Box C104)
      - [Envelope labeled: Vanguard -- AFA films], 1969 (Folder 17c)
        Correspondence with Maynard Solomon of the Vanguard Recording Society regarding the use of his music for the American Federation of Arts (AFA) films Light and the Country and Light and the City. Also includes a copy of the agreement between Hurwitz and Vanguard and related notes.
    - no title (Box C218)
      - [AFA film scripts, shooting outline for "Color Film #1], 1967 (Folder 1a)
        Scripts for "Film #1 on Color," "Film #2 on Color," "Film #3 on Point of View," shooting outline for "Color Film #1" bound in a blue folder.
      - Color #1 Cutting Notes -- Neg. Log, #1, 2, 4, 1968 (Folder 1b)
        Cutting notes.
      - Address, etc. from cutting room wall, 1967-1968 (Folder 1c)
        Newspaper clippings on the draft screening of In Search of Hart Crane, Lee Harvey Oswald; notes; contact information.
      - Color -- notes for film, 1967 (Folder 1d)
        Notes prepared for the American Federation of Arts (AFA) by Roemer-Young Associates; idea summary for the "Color" script.
      - [Sequence notes, AFA scripts, ideas and outline for color film], 1967 (Folder 1e)
        Notes on the dawn and night sequences; cover letter from AFA and scripts for "Film #1 on Color," "Film #2 on Color," "Film #3 on Point of View," and shooting outline for "Color Film #1"; location notes for "Film #3"; ideas and outline for color film.
      - ["Color Film #1" arrangement of sequence material], 1968 (Folder 1f)
        "Color #1" arrangement of material into categories; notes from original log and screening order.
    - no title (Box C221)
      - [Envelope labeled: AFA -- letters from and to Rudi, script notes, etc. on country film], 1969 (Folder 3a)
        Correspondence between Hurwitz and Rudolf Arnheim on the shaping of the film Light and the Country and Light and the City; script notes.
      - 2nd notes --City and Country, 1969 (Folder 3b)
        Logs for Light and the City and Light and the Country; shot list
      - Editing notes -- AFA Film 1 -- country and sea, morn to night, 1969 (Folder 3b.1)
        Editing notes and rental receipts.
      - Mix logs --Light and the City/Country, also Discovery in a Landscape(return), 1969 (Folder 3c)
        Mix logs and list of mix elements, film loops for transfer; narrative script with notes.
      - [Letter from Rudolf Arnheim], 1969 (Folder 3d)
        Letter to Hurwitz from Rudolf Arnheim confirming that the two films (Light and the City and Light and the Country) seem acceptable for the purposes of the AFA series.
      - Logs -- SFX --City and Country, 1969 (Folder 3e)
        Titles for Light and the Country with sound effects logs; loops of sounds and sound logs.
      - [Light and the City-- remix log], ca. 1969; 1975 (Folder 3f)
        Log for remix of music and sound effects for Light and the City.
      - [Envelope labeled: Narration --City,Country], 1969 (Folder 3g)
        Narration scripts for Light and the City and Light and the Country, draft of script titled "Light on the City"; thought script "City Light from Dusk to Dawn" by Arnheim; notes from rewrite of Light and the City.
      - Editing notes -- AFA film 1A -- city, morn to night, 1969 (Folder 3h)
        Notes from cutting room table during cutting of Light and the City and Light and the Country; notes about organization of film material; editing notes; notes after showing of sample material and correspondence from Rudolf Arnheim with suggestions.
    - no title (Box C227)
      - Music -- Cezanne, long version, 1968 (Folder 27)
        List of music listened to.
    - no title (Box OS-8)
      - [Brown paper wrapping labeled: Title cards:Light and the City,Light in the Country], ca. 1968 (Folder 3)
        Title cards for the films Light and the City and Light and the Country: transparencies and cardboard cards.
      - [Brown paper wrapping labeled: Leo Hurwitz title cards Landscape,Painting], ca. 1969 (Folder 4)
        Title cards for Discovery in a Landscape,Journey into a Painting, and Discovery in a Painting, with tissue-paper overlays.
  - Subseries 3,China Strikes Back, 1938-1982; 1938/1939
    - no title (Box C005)
      - Native Land-- misc. notes and notebooks, etc., 1938-1939 (Folder 4c)
        Includes a China Strikes Back script.
    - no title (Box C033)
      - Current correspondence -- answer!, 1961-1962; undated (Folder 1)
        Correspondence related to At the Waters' Edge, "The Scarlet Letter," and film elements for Native Land and China Strikes Back. Correspondents include Nazli Nour, Thomas Brandon, and Judith Gold.
    - no title (Box C232)
      - Japan Broadcasting Corp.: correspondence, 1982 (Folder 8)
        Correspondence from NHK/Japan Broadcasting Corp. about the possibility of using footage from China Strikes Back in their documentary program The War Was Like This.
  - Subseries 4,Cover Girl in Paris, 1963-1965
    - no title (Box C075)
      - [Envelope labeled: Material for mix --Cover Girl], 1964 (Folder 3)
        Mixing log, for the long version of Cover Girl.
    - no title (Box C227)
      - Drafts --Cover Girl script, 1963-1965 (Folder 3)
        Draft scripts by Hurwitz for Cover Girl in Paris, and final version sent by Helen Nash Associates; pamphlet "Cover Girl Make-Up Tips."
      - [Envelope labeled: "Cover Girl" scripts], 1964/1965 (Folder 4)
        Correspondence between Hurwitz and Helen Nash and draft narration scripts for "A Cover Girl's Paris" [final title Cover Girl in Paris].
  - Subseries 5,Dialogue with a Woman Departed, 1942-1991; 1971-1989
    - no title (Box C001)
      - Dialogue W.A.W.D. Prints -- Made at Filmtronics Lab, 1978; 1981; undated (Folder 12)
        Notes and correspondence with Filmtronics regarding print material of Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - Dialogue W.A.W.D. Eastman Kodak -- re: soundtrack faults in early prints, 1981 (Folder 13)
        Receipt, notes, and correspondence with Eastman Kodak regarding prints of Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - Distribution --D.W.A.W.D., 1981-1983 (Folder 14)
        Correspondence regarding foreign distribution of Dialogue with a Woman Departed. In English and French.
      - Interested inquires --D.W.A.W.D., 1981-1983 (Folder 15)
        Correspondence regarding distribution of Dialogue with a Woman Departed, with one letter about Native Land and Heart of Spain.
      - Funding:D.W.A.W.D., 1979 (Folder 16)
        Correspondence between Nelly Burlingham and Carol Bernstein Ferry and representatives of the National Council of the Churches of Christ regarding funding Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - D.W.A.W.D. New distribution thoughts, 1987 (Folder 18)
        Undated prints-outs of notes and ideas regarding Dialogue with a Woman Departed, and the Spring-Summer 1987 issue of Monthly Review Press.
      - Distribution of D.W.A.W.D., 1982-1986; 1989 (Folder 19)
        Notices, invoices, notes, and correspondence with foreign distributors, cinematheques, broadcasters, and ministries regarding Dialogue with a Woman Departed. In English and German.
      - D.W.A.W.D. leads, 1980-1982 (Folder 20)
        Notes, contact information, and correspondence with the Videofilm Centre, Netherlands Broadcasting Corporation, Cinema St. Severin, Contemporary Films, and Bauer International Pictures regarding Dialogue with a Woman Departed. Also includes a Bauer Films catalog.
      - Folkets Bio -- Contract (D.W.A.W.D.) for distribution, etc. – Lisskulla, 1981-1987 (Folder 21)
        Materials related to a contract between Hurwitz and the Swedish distributor Folkets bio for Dialogue with a Woman Departed. Includes contract, correspondence, account statements, notes, contact information, promotional postcards, and a copy of an agreement between FilmCentrum and the Arts Council of Great Britain for the film Dread, Beat an' Blood.
    - no title (Box C004)
      - Press material -- copies to be distributed in these files, 1962-1963; 1975; 1981-1989 (Folder 1)
        Includes reviews and background material for Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - Misc. papers, 1942; 1979-1985; 1989 (Folder 2)
        Includes “Book of Quotes -- Final Copy” for Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - [Dialogue with a Woman Departed press book], 1980-1985 (Folder 3)
        Materials related to Dialogue with a Woman Departed, including reviews, flyers, production information, note on the presentation, and biographical information. Material is in English and French.
      - [Dialogue with a Woman Departed promotional material], 1981 (Folder 4)
        Newsletter mentioning award, Third World Newsreel mailers, and a book of pull quotes praising Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - [Dialogue with a Woman Departed press material and "Search (Who Was John Brown)" synopsis], 1982-1983 (Folder 5)
        Materials related to Dialogue with a Woman Departed, including reviews, correspondence, flyers, and a program from the National Film Theatre, London. Also includes a synopsis for Hurwitz's proposed John Brown film.
      - [Dialogue with a Woman Departed press folder--The Public Theater, New York City], 1982 (Folder 6)
        Folder compiled for screenings of Dialogue with a Woman Departed at the Public Theater on February 19-28, 1982. Materials include review, programing announcement from WBAI-FM, flyers, schedule, press release, a recollection of Peggy Lawson, and a response to Discovery in a Landscape that was handed to Hurwitz during the screenings
      - Materials for layout samples for D.W.A.W.D. press kit, 1981-1985 (Folder 7)
        Materials related to the Dialogue with a Woman Departed press kit, including text, suggested poster copy, reviews, and the National Film Theatre schedule.
      - Layout samples --D.W.A.W.D. press kit -- copies -- b&w for 3rd World, 1982 (Folder 9)
        Dialogue with a Woman Departed press-kit layout, including sample text, notes, reviews, covers, and images.
      - Original press kit layouts -- color --D.W.A.W.D., 1982 (Folder 10)
        Dialogue with a Woman Departed press release, reviews, press kit layout sheets, and notes.
      - Work material: “responses” and notes on presentation, 1981 (Folder 11a)
        Responses to Dialogue with a Woman Departed from critics and others, and a draft of the presentation of the film for distributors and exhibitors.
      - WBAI-FM copy for Folio -- letter re: contribution -- N.Y. opening, 1981-1982 (Folder 11b)
        Correspondence with Mary Robbins [WBAI radio], notes from a lunch with Rick Harris [WBAI radio], and copies of WBAI's Folio magazine; box-office summary; notes; and Dialogue with a Woman Departed soundtrack information.
      - Letters, etc. commenting on Dialogue with a Woman Departed, 1977-1978 (Folder 11c)
        Dialogue with a Woman Departed related correspondence with Gayla Jamison [IMAGE Film & Video Center], Allen F. Davis [Temple University], Christian Lehmann, Manny Kirchheimer, Hilary Harris, and Harry Magdoff [Monthly Review].
      - Portuguese -- reviews -- responses -- letters -- photos -- Sept. ‘81, 1981 (Folder 11d)
        Reviews and responses to Dialogue with a Woman Departed in Portuguese, with notes in English. Also includes a photograph of Hurwitz, and correspondence with "Connie," with an English translation.
      - Dutch reviews, 1981 (Folder 12a)
        Dutch newspaper reviews of Dialogue with a Woman Departed. In Dutch, with no translation.
      - Audience responses February 1982, NYC -- N.Y opening -- letters (Folder 12b)
        Correspondence following the New York City screening of Dialogue with a Woman Departed, including a card from the Department of Film at the Museum of Modern Art.
      - Responses to D.W.A.W.D., 1980-1982 (Folder 12c)
        Reactions to Dialogue with a Woman Departed in the form of reviews, newspaper clippings, and correspondence, including an English translation of a letter from Christian Lehmann to Manny Kirchheimer. Materials are in English, Dutch, German, and Finnish. Also includes an issue of Andere Sinema [in Dutch with some English translations].
      - “New” responses and reviews from Fall 1981 (Folder 12d)
        Correspondence, reviews, and notices regarding Dialogue with a Woman Departed. Materials are in English, Swedish, and French.
    - no title (Box C006)
      - Script -- log --Dialogue with a Woman Departed as of 10/29/77, 1977 (Folder 14)
        Bound script with notes.
      - [Dialogue with a Woman Departed production materials], 1980 (Folder 7)
        Dialogue with a Woman Departed production notes and letters from Tom McGrath.
    - no title (Box C008)
      - N.Y. ad page, 1982 (Folder 11c)
        Copies of ads for Dialogue with a Woman Departed placed in Guardian,Village Voice,Soho News, and The New York Times.
      - Weinberg review (Films in Review), 1982 (Folder 12d)
        Copies of a review of Dialogue with a Woman Departed from Herman Weinberg's column “The Weinberg Touch” published in Films in Review in April 1982.
      - WBAI:Folio paragraph and announcements; Daily News: Note, 1982 (Folder 12e)
        Copies of notices about Dialogue with a Woman Departed from Daily News and WBAI-FM's Folio.
      - Letters: Remedios, Gohsman, van der Heide; Rosemary Willey: Poem, 1981; 1982; 1984 (Folder 12f)
        Copies of a poem by Willey about Dialogue with a Woman Departed, responses to Hurwitz concerning that film.
      - Box office statements (Public Theater), 1982 (Folder 12g)
        Materials related to the exhibition of Dialogue with a Woman Departed, including box-office reports, copies of newspaper ads from The Guardian,Soho News,Village Voice, and The New York Times.
      - Sweden reviews -- copies, 1982 (Folder 14)
        Photocopies of clippings from Swedish newspaper articles regarding Dialogue with a Woman Departed, with English translations of full reviews.
      - French clippings: Épernay -- copies, 1983 (Folder 15)
        Copies of French newspaper articles about Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - (Leo Hurwitz) Brief background -- by Nelly Burlingham/Biographical note on Leo Hurwitz -- by Kristin, ca. 1981 (Folder 16a)
      - Two-page résumé plus biographical note, ca. 1981; 1983 (Folder 16b)
      - Critical reviews LH films, ca. 1980 (Folder 16c)
        Reviews of Hurwitz films, list of his principle films, gathered around the time of Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - International Critics Prize/Arts Guardian (London), 1980; 1981 (Folder 16d)
        Copies of Guardian summation of Dialogue with a Woman Departed and notice about the film’s appearance at the London Film Festival, flyers announcing the awarding of a prize to the film at the Berlin Film Festival.
      - Note re: presentation, ca. 1980 (Folder 16e)
        Note on the presentation of Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - Recollection of Peggy, ca. 1980 (Folder 17)
        Copies of “A Recollection of Peggy Lawson” by Peter Gessner, dating from the time of the production of Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - Account of career, ca. 1980 (Folder 18)
      - Credits:D.W.A.W.D./Principle films, ca. 1980 (Folder 19)
        Credits for Dialogue with a Woman Departed and list of Hurwitz’s principle films.
      - Brochure idea/D.W.A.W.D./“Book of Quotes” -- layouts, ca. 1980 (Folder 2)
        Drafts of brochure and "Book of Quotes" for promotion of Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - [Envelope labeled: Derek Malcolm review -- Guardian¬ -- London Film Festival], 1980 (Folder 21)
        Several copies of the Malcolm review of the London Film Festival, with reference to Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - Copies: miscellaneous -- press clippings, 1981-1985 (Folder 23)
        Copies of press clippings for Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - [Dialogue with a Woman Departed promotional and background material], 1980 (Folder 25)
        Promotional flyers from Third World Newsreel and Peter Gessner's note about Peggy Lawson.
      - Transcripts from tapes (by C.S.) re:D.W.A.W.D., 1982 (Folder 3)
        Transcripts of interviews with Hurwitz conducted by Rick Harris (WBAI) and Leslie Peters (WNYC), as well as audience responses to Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
    - no title (Box C009)
      - [Envelope labeled: Sweden: Folkets Bio -- skimpy press material and Film Institute programs], 1982-1985 (Folder 1)
        Correspondence and press materials regarding Dialogue with a Woman Departed and programs for the showing of Hurwitz films in Sweden. Material is from the Swedish distribution company Folkets Bio and the Swedish Film Institute [Svenska Filminstitutet].
      - Press clippings Köln-Bócst of Dialogue with a Woman Departed, 1982 (Folder 2)
        German press clippings and press release regarding the film Dialogue with a Woman Departed. In German.
      - [Dialogue with a Woman Departed promotional material/general career material], 1974-1985 (Folder 3)
        Poster copy, clippings, and promotional materials for Dialogue with a Woman Departed. Additional materials include general clippings, copies of the Hurwitz articles “One Man’s Voyage: Ideas and Films in the 1930s” and “The Influence of Soviet Silent Cinema,” brief transcripts of interviews, film festival program, and résumé.
      - [Dialogue with a Woman Departed-- distribution material], 1981-1986 (Folder 4)
        Correspondence, distribution agreements, receipts, expense reports, and other distribution materials for Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - [Dialogue with a Woman Departed-- promotional material layouts], 1981-1982 (Folder 5)
        Pull-quotes and excerpts from reviews of Dialogue with a Woman Departed, cut and pasted into layouts for promotional materials.
      - Press clipping and advertising -- NYC opening --Dialogue with a Woman Departed, 1982 (Folder 6)
        Correspondence, press clippings, broadcast transcripts, advertisements, all regarding Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - Dialogue with a Woman Departed-- NYC opening press clippings, 1982 (Folder 7)
        Press clippings regarding Dialogue with a Woman Departed from Folio magazine, published by WBAI.
      - London ’82 -- National Film Theatre retrospective, 1982 (Folder 8)
        Materials regarding a 1982 retrospective of Hurwitz's work in London. National Film Theater programs and notes, film catalog from The Other Cinema, BFI publications, correspondence, clippings, customs documents, and signed photograph of Jane Dudley.
    - no title (Box C016)
      - Godfrey's fundraising -- our copies, 1979 (Folder 18)
        Correspondence regarding filmmaker Godfrey Reggio and funding for Dialogue with a Woman Departed. Includes copies of cover letters that accompanied promotional material, notes, and contact list.
      - Copies for sending L.H. promo material, ca. 1980 (Folder 19)
        Promotional background material for Dialogue with a Woman Departed, including a production note, a brief background on Hurwitz, and a list of his principle films. Includes edits.
      - [Dialogue with a Woman Departed production publication and correspondence], 1976; undated (Folder 2)
        Dialogue with a Woman Departed investment prospectus, with biographical notes, investment terms, and a proposed budget. Correspondence lists possible distributors.
      - Tour -- Europe -- Fall, 1980 (Folder 20)
        Materials related to Dialogue with a Woman Departed and its European exhibition, including notes, receipts, correspondence, background on Hurwitz, and the film's entry into the London Film Festival.
      - London Film Festival, 1980 (Folder 21)
        Programs for the 24th London Film Festival, correspondence, and an entry form for Dialogue with a Woman Departed.
      - Plus corrected older versions, ca. 1980 (Folder 22)
        Promotional background material for Dialogue with a Woman Departed, such as a note on the production, a brief background on Hurwitz, and a list of his principle films. All copies, no originals.
    - no title (Box C018)
      - Correspondence, 1975; 1977; undated (Folder 3a)
        Correspondence, mostly concerning Dialogue with a Woman Departed.Native Land is occasionally mentioned in the context of retrospective screenings.
    - no title (Box C021)
      - [Bag labeled: Original and copy text: D.W.A.W.D], ca. 1981 (Folder 16)
        Text for the film Dialogue with a Woman Departed, master copy with slight corrections and bound photocopy with corrected text.
      - For Lani -- trial words -- as of 5/5/76 -- R 4, 5, 6, 7 -- "S.F.N.P.", 1976 (Folder 18)